Damien Couroussé

Research Engineer Embedded Software and Embedded Security

Research I am interested in embedded software and its interaction with hardware: Compilers, interpreters interests and runtime code generation for performance and cyber-security purposes, Countermeasures against side-channel attacks and fault injection attacks, Hardware and software co-design for secure processor design.

Experience

2011-now Research Engineer, CEA, Grenoble, France.

Leading a team of 6-8 people, in a highly pluri-disciplinary environment, for a large French RTO. Design of Software and Hardware countermeasures for hardware security.

- o Project coordination of research collaborative projects: COGITO (ANR 2013-2017), CLAPs (IRT NanoElec, Pulse program, 2018-2020); Work-package leader in a large european project: SERENE-IoT. I was involved in many French and European Research Projects involving academics and industrial parties.
- o Co-author of scientific publications in the fields of embedded software, side-channel attacks, faultinjection attacks, compilation, runtime code generation, high-performance embedded software, micro-architecture software optimizations.
- Co-inventor of 6 patents (3 others pending).
- Supervised 3 Ph.D students, 3 post-doc students, 4 research engineers, 16 masters students.
- External reviewer for international conferences: DAC, DATE.

2009-2010

Technical Expert, Logica, Grenoble, France, Principal engineer in an 'embedded software' team.

- Scientific contributor to two European research projects. Representative person for Logica.
- o For STMicroelectronics Grenoble: For Set-Top Boxes, prototyping a resource manager with kernel (Linux, RT-OS) and userland APIs. Porting of a test framework for a video middleware.
- o For Gorgy Timing: Development of a Linux driver for a PHY ethernet component, for high-resolution clocks distributed over networks.
- o Building answers to requests for proposals, training and mentoring of Junior engineers.

2004–2008 PhD student & Research Engineer, ICA Laboratory, Grenoble, France.

- o Design and implementation of a real-time multi-sensory simulator (haptics, sound and image) of mechanical objects, as a research and creation platform for instrumental interaction
 - Software development of a multi-sensory simulator Real-time programming (DSP TI-C67x), systems programming (C, Linux, ADC/DAC), graphics programming.
 - Psychophysics experiments, in collaboration with Gunnar Jansson, Professor Emeritus at Uppsala Univ., Sweden.
- o Research collaborator and assistant of the deputee coordinator in a large european research project: Enactive Interfaces (consortium of 26 members).
- Participation to a startup project (Ergos Technologies): software deliveries, user trainings and user support. Design of demonstrators.
- 2004–2008 **Teaching Assistant**, *Univ. Pierre-Mendès France*, Grenoble, France, (*moniteur*, *ATER*). Computer architecture, operating systems, networks, analysis and modeling of information systems.
- 2003–2002 **Software Engineer**, ICA Laboratory, Grenoble, France.

Development of a Linux driver for a PCI acquisition board including an on-board DSP.

Education

- 2004–2008 **Ph.D(Tech)**, *INPG*, Grenoble, France, Art, Sciences and Technologies, with honors.. Research director: Annie Luciani, Scientific supervisor: Jean-Louis Florens.
- 2002–2003 **DEA Sciences Cognitives**, (Master's Degree), INPG, Grenoble, France, Mention Très-Bien.
- 1997–2002 **Master's Degree**, Engineering diploma. Electronics & Communication Systems, INSA, Rennes, France.

Programming skills

Programming C, Haskell, C++, assembly (ARM, RISC-V), Python, Systems programming (Linux, baremetal)

Selected publications

I have co-authored 4 journal articles, 8 contributions to scientific books, chapters & booklets, 25 papers in international conferences, peer-reviewed with proceedings, 12 contributions to international workshops with peer-reviewed selection. I gave 8 invited talks or keynotes.

I am the co-inventor of 6 patents; 3 other patent applications are pending.

Compilation of software countermeasures against side-channel and fault injection attacks

- Nicolas Belleville, Damien Couroussé, Karine Heydemann, and Henri-Pierre Charles. "Automated Software Protection for the Masses Against Side-Channel Attacks". In: ACM TACO 15.4 (Jan. 2019), 47:1–47:27
- Nicolas Belleville, Karine Heydemann, Damien Couroussé, Thierno Barry, Bruno Robisson, Abderramane Seriai, and Henri-Pierre Charles. "Automatic Application of Software Countermeasures Against Physical Attacks". In: Cyber-Physical Systems Security. Springer, Dec. 2018, pp. 135–155
- Thierno Barry, Damien Couroussé, and Bruno Robisson. "Compilation of a Countermeasure Against Instruction-Skip Fault Attacks". In: Proceedings of the Third Workshop on Cryptography and Security in Computing Systems (CS2). Prague, Jan. 2016
- Thierno Barry, Damien Couroussé, Karine Heydeman, and Bruno Robisson. Automated Combination of Tolerance and Control Flow Integrity Countermeasures against Multiple Fault Attacks. 2017 European LLVM Developers Meeting. Sarrbrücken, Germany, Mar. 2017

Detection of attacks on IoT devices

 Sanaa Kerroumi, Damien Couroussé, Florian Pebay-Peyroula, Mohammed Benaoud, and Anca Molnos. On the applicability of binary classification to detect memory access attacks in IoT. C&ESAR. Rennes, Nov. 2018

Simulation of processor micro-architectures

- o Fernando Akira Endo, Damien Couroussé, and Henri-Pierre Charles. "Pushing the Limits of Online Auto-tuning: Machine Code Optimization in Short-Running Kernels". In: CoRR abs/1707.04566 (2017)
- Fernando Endo, Damien Couroussé, and Henri-Pierre Charles. "Micro-architectural simulation of in-order and out-of-order ARM microprocessors with gem5". In: Embedded Computer Systems: Architectures, Modeling, and Simulation (SAMOS XIV), 2014 International Conference on. Greece, July 2014, pp. 266– 273
- Fernando A. Endo, Damien Couroussé, and Henri-Pierre Charles. "Micro-architectural Simulation of Embedded Core Heterogeneity with Gem5 and McPAT". in: Proceedings of the 2015 Workshop on Rapid Simulation and Performance Evaluation: Methods and Tools. RAPIDO '15. Amsterdam, Holland: ACM, 2015, 7:1–7:6

Code optimization for performance

- o Fernando Akira Endo, Damien Couroussé, and Henri-Pierre Charles. "Pushing the Limits of Online Auto-tuning: Machine Code Optimization in Short-Running Kernels". In: *CoRR* abs/1707.04566 (2017)
- Henri-Pierre Charles, Damien Couroussé, Victor Lomüller, Fernando A. Endo, and Rémy Gauguey. "deGoal a Tool to Embed Dynamic Code Generators into Applications". In: *Compiler Construction*. Ed. by Albert Cohen. Vol. 8409. Lecture Notes in Computer Science. Springer, 2014, pp. 107–112

File built Tue, 5 Mar 2019 23:21:11 +0100